[The Age of Awakening]
[觉醒年代]
[Episode Thirty-one]
[第三十一集]
The reason why I brought Peking University up
我之所以把北大提出来
Moving south to Shanghai
[陈独秀 字 仲甫 北京大学教授]
I want to keep Peking University.
我为的就是要把北大保留下来
Stay in Qingshan
留得青山在
Not afraid of burning wood.
不怕没柴烧
That's all I am.
我仅此而已
This is a compromise.
你这是妥协
It's surrender
是投降
The reason why China is so timid
中国之所以这么窝囊
Because Guo Xingang is too little.
就是因为郭心刚太少
There are too many Shi.
胡适之太多了
中富兄
仲甫兄
You calm down.
你息怒
I rashly proposed to move Peking University to Shanghai.
我贸然提出来要把北大南迁上海
Without consulting with you.
没有跟你商量
I was wrong.
是我不对
Now the proposal and signature letter
现在倡议书和签名信
It's all burnt down.
都已经烧毁了
It won't produce any shadow.
也不会产生什么影
Let's call it a day.
今天的话就到此为止吧
I'll buy you a drink another day.
改天我请你喝酒
proffer a birch and ask for punishment by flogging―offer a humble and sincere apology
负荆请罪
Excuse me
失陪了
Let's go. The police are coming. Let's go.
快走 警察来了 快走
Liu Mei
柳眉
Chen Yannian
陈延年
go
走
Yannian
延年
brother
哥
Liu Mei
柳眉
Yannian
延年
brother
哥
刘梅姐
柳眉
Yannian
延年
brother
哥
Who are you looking for in the dark?
黑灯瞎火的你们找什么人啊
Hello, uncle.
你好 大叔
We are looking for two children.
我们找两个孩子
A man and a woman are both in their twenties.
一男一女 都二十来岁
It's a lecture student, right?
是演讲的学生吧
Yes, I gave a speech here this afternoon.
是下午是在这儿演讲过
I said you should stop shouting here.
我说你们别在这儿喊了
The students who give speeches here will not be driven away.
这儿演讲的学生要不被赶走了
Otherwise, they would have been taken away.
要不早就被抓走了
Then where else can we look?
那我们还能上哪儿找找去啊
You guys?
你们哪
I think I'd better try my luck at Dashilan.
我看还是去大栅栏那边碰碰运气吧
There are many shops over there
那边商铺多
Dashilan
大栅栏
right
对
Okay, thanks.
好 谢谢啊
Just turn that way.
往那边一拐就是
Yannian
延年
Be careful.
小心点啊
hold one's own
坚持住
Did you hear what I said?
听见我说话了吗
You hear me? Hang in there
听见没 坚持住
It'll be all right.
不会有事的
Be sure to hold on.
一定要坚持住
Yannian
延年
Chen Yannian
陈延年
Liu Mei
柳眉
Uncle Chen auntie
陈伯伯 姨妈
We are here.
我们在这儿
Liu Mei
柳眉
Uncle Chen auntie, we are here.
陈伯伯 姨妈 我们在这儿
Yannian was injured by the cavalry.
延年被马队打伤了
Wounded
延年
Unconscious
不省人事了
Hurry to the hospital.
快点送医院
Come on, get up
快点 快 快起来
Come and help
来 帮忙
Send to hospital
送医院
come
来
rise
起来
come on
快 来
come
来
Qiaonian held an umbrella for them.
乔年 给他们撑着伞
go
走
Go that way.
走那边
Why are you up?
你怎么起来了
Sit down quickly
快坐下
sit down
坐下
lie down
躺下
Why am I here?
我怎么在这儿啊
You were wounded by the police.
你被警察打伤了
Close to the French hospital
离法国医院近
I sent you here.
我就把你送过来了
not bad
还好
Mild concussion
轻度脑震荡
Liu Mei, where are they?
柳眉他们呢
Liu Mei suffered a little back injury.
柳眉后背受了一点伤
Got some cold.
受了些凉
Some fever.
有些发烧
He's also in the hospital.
也住在医院了
But the doctor said it was okay.
不过医生说还好
Both of you are fine.
你们两个都无大碍
Just rest for a few days.
静养几日就好了
What about me auntie
那我姨妈呢
Why are you here alone?
怎么你一个人在这儿
I
我
I sent you here yesterday.
我昨天把你送来
What happened yesterday inspired me a little.
昨天的事情对我有一些启发
Inspired
有灵感
Want to write an article
想写一篇文章
Shandong Problems and National Consciousness
《山东问题和国民觉悟》
It's raining hard.
那雨挺大的
I just want to do it all at once.
我就想一气呵成
Just finish writing here.
在这儿写完算了
I never went back.
就没回去
Want to hear it?
想听听吗
Let me read you a paragraph.
我给你念一段
eh
嗯
Now the warlords of China and Japan
现在 中日两国的军阀
Are they all enemies of justice?
不都是公理的仇敌吗
Civilians of both countries
两国的平民
If you don't have to force them down.
若不用强力将他们打倒
Whatever you want.
任凭你怎样
Shout about axioms every day.
天天把公理挂在嘴上喊叫
We can't advocate abandoning justice by force.
我们不可主张用强力弃公理
But we can't help advocating strong support for justice.
却不可不主张用强力拥护公理
We don't advocate using force to crush people.
我们不主张用强力压人
But we have to advocate it.
却不可不主张
Be crushed by people with strong resistance
用强力抵抗被人所压
One person, one nation.
一个人 一民族
Without the strength of self-defense
若没有自卫的强力
Just hope that justice will flourish.
单只望公理昌明
Rely on the grace of others' forgiveness and help
仰仗人家饶恕和帮助的恩惠
To survive.
才能生存
How humble and shameless this is!
这是何等卑弱无耻
A self-reliant slave
不能自立的奴才
Do you agree with me?
你认同我的观点吗
ah
啊
What do you mean, always?
你总啊是什么意思啊
agree
同意
But some people don't agree.
可是有些人却不同意
Who?
谁呀
I called that back.
那个被我叫回来
You are regarded as a young mentor
被你们奉为青年导师的
Professor Hu Shi
胡适教授
You are both up.
你们俩都起了
auntie
姨妈
How's it going? Any better?
怎么样 好些没
much better
好多了
Chen Bobo is good.
陈伯伯好
Are you feeling better?
你好些没
much better
好多了
Are you okay? Are you still dizzy?
还好吗 头还晕不晕啊
What about you?
你呢
I'm fine.
我还好啦
What were you two talking about just now?
你们爷俩刚才聊什么呢
Let me put down the small table.
让我放下小桌吧
I just wrote an article to read to him.
我刚写了篇文章 给他念念
Say you are really ignorant.
你说你是真不懂事
Still not sensible?
还是假不懂事啊
My son just woke up.
儿子刚刚醒
What article do you read to him?
你给他念什么文章啊
And wanted him to take to the streets.
还想让他上街游行去
auntie
姨妈
Do you still organize street speeches?
还组织上街演讲吗
I really don't know this.
这个我还真不清楚
I knew that Qiaonian was caught in the rain last night.
我就知道乔年昨天晚上也淋了雨
A little cold, too
也有点伤风
I let him lie at home.
我让他在家躺着呢
Yannian
延年
You may not know.
你可能不知道
last night
昨天晚上
Your father took you from the street himself.
是你爸爸亲自把你从大街上
Back to the hospital.
背到医院来的
I wanted to stay and watch you.
本来我想留下来看着你
Your dad didn't agree to kick me out.
你爸不同意 把我给轰走了
Want to stay alone?
要一个人留下来
I've been watching you all night.
守了你一宿呢
Later, I wanted to
后来我还本来想
What are you talking about?
你说这些什么
I'll leave when you come.
你来了 我就走了
Yasheng said that he would give an injection in the morning. Watch this.
矢生说上午还打针 你看着
I'll go to the red chamber to print this.
我去红楼把这个印出来
It's killing me.
不要命了
Look at your whole body.
你自己看看你这一身儿
Can't you go home for dinner and sleep?
你就不能回家吃个饭睡个觉
Change clothes before you go.
换身衣服再去呀
Can't take care of it
顾不上了
The earth won't turn without you, will it?
这地球离了你就不转了是不是
Don't say I'm leaving at this time.
你还别说 这个时候我要离开
It's really possible that it won't turn.
还真有可能转不动了
this
这
Yannian
延年
Let's eat first
先吃饭吧
good
好
Instruction of Ministry of Education
教育部训令
According to Premier Qian Nengxun
根据国务总理钱能训
Signed reply order
签署的批复令
In view of the present situation of various schools in Beijing before taking the initiative
鉴于冒前北京各个学校的现状
Ministry of Education decided
教育部决定
Schools in Beijing will suspend classes from now on.
自即日起 北京各校停课
Early summer vacation
提前放暑假
And the graduating class of each school
而各校的毕业班
The graduation exam will be held as usual.
则照常举行毕业考试
Students who do not take the graduation exam are not allowed to graduate.
不参加毕业考试的学生不得毕业
Ministry of Education of the Republic of China
中华民国教育部
They really know how to play hardball.
他们还真是知道软硬兼施啊
What was hard yesterday is soft today.
昨天来硬的 今天来软的
It's a walk, a walk, a test.
这招走的走 考的考
It's really our weakness.
还真是掐准了我们的软肋
Mr. Shouchang, how do you say this
守常先生 此话怎讲
You want to have a school holiday?
你想 学校放假了
It also means all the normal activities of the school.
也就意味着学校的一切正常活动
It all stopped.
就都停止了
The library has stopped and the canteen has stopped.
图书馆停了 食堂停了
The teacher went home.
教员回家了
Then it will be given to students.
那么就会给学生
Caused great difficulties.
造成了很大的困难
Besides, since it's a holiday.
另外 既然都放假了
So always strike
那么总罢课
It has little to do with the government.
就和政府没有太大关系了
What is going on?
是这么回事
In addition, the graduating class students have to take the exam.
另外毕业班的同学还得参加考试
The study of this graduating class
这次毕业班的同学
The total number of Lu strike three-thirds.
卢了总罢课人数的三分之一
If they don't take the exam
如果他们不参加考试
Then you won't get your diploma.
那么就拿不到毕业证
Can't get a diploma
拿不到毕业证
It's hard to find a job.
就很难找到工作
For their own future.
他们为了自己的前途考虑
Be sure to take the exam.
肯定要参加考试
But once you take the exam
可是一旦参加考试
It also means that they are going to resume classes.
也就说明他们要复课了
Then the general strike will collapse.
那么总罢课也就瓦解了
That's a tough move.
这招还真够狠的
What do you think we should do next?
那您看我们下一步怎么办
the country is in peril
国将不国
This group of superior people only know
这群上位者却只知道
Use soft knives on patriots.
在爱国人士身上使软刀子
Too little of our determination and will.
太小看我们的决心和意志了
Inform student officers and professors.
通知学生干事和教授团
Go to the library for a meeting.
去图书馆开会
Let's discuss the next step.
我们商量下一步对策
Okay, I'm on my way.
好我这就去
classmates
同学们
Since the Ministry of Education announced the suspension of classes
自教育部发布停课
And the instructions for graduates to take the exam as usual.
和毕业生照常考试的训令之后
It has a great influence on schools.
对各校影响极大
Beijing Agricultural College
北京农业专科学校
Law school and other schools.
法政专科学校等学校的
Many fresh graduates
许多应届毕业生
The strike was cancelled automatically.
都自动取消了罢课
In addition, the State Council issued
此外 国务院发布
About civil service in advance
关于提前进行文官
And the news of the diplomatic judicial examination.
和外交司法官考试的消息
Also among some students.
也在一部分同学中
Had a negative impact.
产生了消极影响
Look today.
今天看
The number of students on strike dropped sharply.
罢课学生人数锐减
same time
同时
Because of the severe repressive measures taken by the government
由于政府采取严厉的镇压措施
Wei part of the students' psychology.
威慑了一部分同学的心理
Combined with military and police blockade.
加之军警的封锁阻拦
Today, a group of ten students from each school
今天各校十人团
All the demonstrations and speeches on the streets were cancelled.
全部取消了上街游行演讲的活动
What should I do next?
下一步该怎么办
We must find effective ways and means.
我们必须找到有效的方式方法
Otherwise, the struggle will be unsustainable.
否则斗争根本难以为继
中富兄
仲甫兄
Isn't Yannian injured?
延年不是受伤了吗
What are you doing here?
你上这儿来干什么
Have you been diagnosed? What did the doctor say?
确诊了吗 医生怎么说
it doesn't matter
没事
Yasheng checked, and it's fine.
矢生检查过了 无大碍
Haiwei
海威
This was last night.
这是昨天晚上
I wrote an article in the hospital.
我在医院写的一篇文章
You have someone carve wax paper and print leaflets.
你找人刻蜡纸 印传单
Send it out today
今天散发出去
good
好
Hai Wei, don't worry.
海威 先别着急
中富兄
仲甫兄
Now the streets are full of military police and cavalry.
现在大街上全是军警和马队
Banning speeches and distributing leaflets.
明令禁止演讲 还有散发传单
I read your article.
我看 你这篇文章
Don't print it for now.
暂时不要印发了
The situation is really tense now.
现在形势真的非常紧张
We can't push on like this.
我们不能这样硬顶下去了
Go on like this
这样下去
A heavy loss outweighs the gain.
损失惨重 得不偿失啊
I was up all night
适之 我一夜没睡
I wrote this article.
我写的这篇文章
Just want to give someone like you
就是想给像你这样
Dare not talk to the reactionary government
不敢跟反动政府
The right people look at it
作对的人看的
Haiwei
海威
Read it to everyone.
你念念给大家听听
good
好
Our nationals are the Shandong issue.
我们国民为山东问题
There should be two kinds of thorough consciousness.
应该有两种彻底的觉悟
We can't rely solely on axiomatic consciousness.
一 不能单纯地依赖公理的觉悟
Can't let a few people
二 不能让少数人
Awareness of monopoly regime
垄断政权的觉悟
By this thorough awakening
由这彻底的觉悟
We should have two purposes in mind.
就应当抱定两大宗旨
Is to strongly support justice.
就是强力拥护公理
Civilians conquer the government
平民征服政府
Good point!
说得好
Now this situation
现在这种情况
That's all I need.
就需要这么一记棒喝
Why do you have to go to extremes?
你们为什么一定要走极端呢
Why do you have to do this?
为什么一定要做这种
What about meaningless sacrifice?
无谓的牺牲呢
that
那个
Have you heard from Lian?
学联那面有消息了吗
Zhongxia, they have gone to the meeting.
中夏他们已经去开会了
We are discussing countermeasures.
我们正在商量对策
What do you think?
你有什么想法
My attitude is shown in this article.
我的态度都表明在这篇文章里了
Struggle resolutely
坚决斗争
Of course, we should also consider Shizhi's opinion.
当然 也要考虑一下适之的意见
Don't make unnecessary sacrifices.
不能做无谓的牺牲
I agree with Mr. Zhongfu's proposal.
我赞成仲甫先生所提出的
Strongly support axioms
强力拥护公理
The slogan of conquering the government by civilians
平民征服政府的口号
We must never give in.
我们绝对不能屈服于
The ferocity of the reactionaries
反动派的淫威
So tomorrow, our schools will
这样 明天我们各校的
Luyidui steet
护鲁义勇队上街
Escort the ten-member group.
为十人团保驾护航
really can't
实在不行
Let's play hardball with the police.
咱们就跟警察来个硬碰硬的
Can't yield to
对 不能屈服
This is brute-force Liu Haiwei.
这是蛮干 刘海威
Can't be foolhardy
不能蛮干
You misinterpreted Mr. Zhongfu's meaning.
你曲解了仲甫先生的意思
Just now, Mr. Yang Fu has made it very clear.
刚才仲甫先生已经说得很明白了
We can't make such unnecessary sacrifices any more.
咱们不能再做这种无谓的牺牲了
We should pay attention to methods and strategies.
咱们要讲究方法 讲究策略
I think at this time
我认为现在这个时候
We must retreat and cancel the strike.
我们一定要以退为进 取消罢课
Take a legal struggle
采取合法的斗争
In your present situation
适之 你现在这种情况
If you take the slide backwards,
如果以退为进的话
That is to cancel the struggle and surrender.
那就是取消斗争 缴械投降了
My Shouchang brother
我的守常兄啊
How can you look like
你怎么会像
Some students are just as reckless.
有的学生一样地莽撞呢
You are a youth tutor.
你是青年导师
What you should do now is to calm down.
你现在应该做的是沉静下来
Instead of adding fuel to the fire
而不是火上浇油啊
Shizhi, you are wrong
适之 你错了
Now is the time to add fuel to the fire.
现在就应该火上浇油
What we should do now is add fuel to the fire.
我们现在做的就应该是火上浇油
Students' patriotic enthusiasm
同学们的爱国热情
It's all burning up.
都已经燃烧起来了
We need to add another fire.
我们要再添一把火
Let it illuminate the whole society.
让它把整个社会照亮
Let the patriotic enthusiasm of all China burn.
让全中国的爱国热情都燃烧起来
So as to save our country.
这样才能救我们这个国家
Good point!
说得好
As students of Peking University
你们作为北京大学的学生
Don't you tell the difference?
青红皂白你们都不分了吗
寿昌兄
守常兄
You have to pay for your applause.
你要为你的叫好声付出代价的
pour oil on the fire
火上浇油
Are you trying to make yourself
你是想让你自己
Is the whole Peking University burned to death?
还有整个北大都被烧死吗
Shizhi
适之
You have opinions and emotions, you come at me.
你有意见 有情绪你冲我来
Are you throwing cold water on everyone?
你在给大家泼冷水吗
We're not going to extremes.
不是我们走极端
Beiyang government is going to extremes.
是北洋政府在走极端
The police wounded the child.
警察打伤了孩子
Took the students, didn't you see?
抓走了学生 你没看见吗
You are a teacher.
你是一名老师
Can you leave it alone?
你可以无动于裹吗
寿昌先生
守常先生
How about Lian?
学联那边怎么样
classmates
同学们
We have just received a telegram from Paris.
刚刚我们收到了来自巴黎的电报
The telegram says
电报上面说
The envoy of Paris is struggling to persist.
巴黎的专使正在苦苦地坚持
Overseas Chinese in Paris are also marching to resist.
巴黎的华侨们也都在游行 抵抗
Please don't give up.
请诸位万万不要放弃
Be sure to stick to it.
一定要坚持下去
So the Beijing Students' Federation
所以 北京学生联合会
The provisional congress unanimously decided
临时代表大会一致决定
Thirty-six affiliated schools continue to strike.
所属的三十六所学校继续罢课
Stick to the struggle to the end.
坚持斗争进行到底
Never give up until you take the risk.
不达冒的决不罢休
good
好
At the same time, the Federation also decided
同时学联还决定
In order to reduce unnecessary sacrifice
为了减少不必要的牺牲
Ten-member group of Beijing schools
北京各校十人团
Cancel demonstrations and demonstrations.
取消游行和示威的活动
It can be replaced by other ways.
可以用别的方式代替
By selling domestic products.
以卖国货的方式
Mobilize citizens to boycott Japanese goods.
动员市民们来抵制日货
Boycott the Paris Peace Treaty
抵制巴黎和约
So please all the students in all classes of Peking University.
所以 请北大各科各班的同学们
Hurry up and prepare domestic products.
抓紧时间准备国货
Shangjie tomorrow
明天上街
classmates
同学们
刚才邓中夏同学
刚才邓中夏同学
Brought the news of the Federation of Students
带来的学联的消息
That's what I just said.
就是刚才我说的
The idea of retreating.
以退为进的主张
Everyone should think it over.
大家要好好考虑一下
Absorb
吸收进去
We respect the opinions of the Federation of Students.
好 我们尊重学联的意见
but
但是
This article "Shandong Problem and National Consciousness"
这篇《山东问题和国民觉悟》
Or should it be published in the Weekly Review?
还是要在《每周评论》上发表
Let's split up.
大家分头行动吧
Go into action
行动起来
Shizhi
适之
I know I was exaggerating just now.
我知道刚才我言重了
In front of your students
当着你学生的面儿
I didn't save you face.
没有给你留面子
You must have emotions in your heart.
你一定心里有情绪
Brother Zhongfu, I know you are dealing with things.
仲甫兄我知道你是以事对事
It doesn't matter to me here.
我这儿没关系
You tell lies.
你说假话
We don't need to tell lies.
我们之间不需要说假话
No matter what kind of mood you have.
不管你有么样的情绪
I have to tell you one more thing.
我都要再跟你说一句
The present situation is at this festival.
现在的形势 在这个褪节上
Do you think our country
你觉得我们这个国家
Can you go back any further?
还可以再后退吗
If you return it again
如果再退
Do we have the face to be citizens of this country?
我们还有脸做这个国家的国民吗
If you can't digest it.
如果你还消化不了
I'll buy you a drink another day.
改天我请你喝酒
Sell domestic products and support domestic products
卖国货了 支持国货
Do you want a large can?
大要罐头吗
Would you like a can?
您要个罐头吗
Sell domestic products
卖国货了
have a look
看一下
This is what you want.
您就要这个吧
Just give me one.
一个 给我一个就行
Thank you
谢谢您
Okay, thank you. Thank you
好 谢谢 谢谢
Please support domestic products. Thank you.
请支持国货 谢谢
Do you want a large can?
大要罐头吗
Do you want cookies?
要饼干吗
Maiguohuo building
卖国货楼
Maiguolou
牙粉 牙刷 罐头
Canned tooth powder
卖国货
Support domestic products
支持国货
Canned tooth powder
牙刷 牙粉 罐头
Toyoda
丰载呀
Chen Duxiu is the general background of the student movement.
陈独秀是学生运动的总后台呀
What about him before?
他以前呢
Cai Yuanpei is used to control students.
是利用蔡元培来控制学生
Now he is using publications to guide students.
[吴炳湘 京师警察厅总监]
Do you have any thoughts about him?
你对他有什么想法吗
I
我
Come sit down.
来 坐下
Take your time and have some tea.
慢慢说 来 喝点茶
good
好
I think the most convenient way
我认为最便捷的办法
Is to move the crime.
就是以动罪
Just arrest him and sentence him.
直接把他抓起来判刑
That won't do.
这可不行
What about Chen Duxiu? It has a great influence on society.
陈独秀呢 在社会上影响太大
If we have no evidence to arrest him rashly
如果我们没有证据贸然抓捕他
Will intensify contradictions.
会激化矛盾
Will cause more unrest.
会引起更大的动乱
Not good
不好 不好 不好
Then try to isolate him.
那就想力法孤立他
Let him be embattled.
让他四面楚歌
Let him have no mind anymore.
让他再也没有心思
To worry about the students.
去操心学生的事
Looks like you've got a great idea.
看来你已经有高招了
Let's talk about it. Let's talk about it
来来 说说看说说看
Chen Duxiu is often grumpy.
陈独秀这个人脾气非常暴躁
Offending people everywhere
到处得罪人
He has many old enemies in Peking University.
他在北大就有很多宿敌
Especially Gu Hongming, Huang Kan and Liu Shipei.
尤其是辜鸿铭 黄侃 刘师培
Wait for a few influential and influential professors.
等几个有影响有地位的教授
Different from his point of view
跟他观点不同
Yeah, Chen Duxiu incited students to play sports.
对陈独秀煽动学生搞运动
Very disapproving.
很不以为然
And Chen Duxiu is now
而且陈独秀现在
I'm no longer a senior of liberal arts at Peking University.
已经不当北大文科的学长了
It is these people who instigate it.
正是策动这些人
It's a good time to go after him.
去找他算账的好时候
You can also preposition opportunity.
同时也可以借此机会
Disintegrate the student movement
瓦解学生运动
Aren't you from Peking University?
你不就是北大的吗
You do this.
这事你来做
I was expelled from Peking University.
总监 我是北大开除的
It's not that I don't want to do it
不是 我不是不愿意做
I speak lightly.
我人微言轻
I'm afraid you have to be your family.
恐怕还得您老人家
Go into battle yourself.
亲自上阵才行
What can you do then?
那你能做些什么
I can find his son.
我可以去找他的儿子
陈独秀他儿子
陈独秀他儿子
right
对
Tell us your opinion
说说看
Chen Duxiu has three men and one woman with the original.
陈独秀跟原配生有三男一女
The eldest son Chen Yannian and the second son Chen Qiaonian
大儿子陈延年 二儿子陈乔年
They all live with him in Beijing now.
现在都在北京跟他住在一起
Her two sons
他的两个儿子
I'm born with Chen Duxiu.
天生跟陈独秀不对付
Especially Chen Yannian.
特别是陈延年
Believe in anarchism.
笃信无政府主义 倔得很
No, I was speaking at the front door the other day.
这不 前两天在前门演讲的时候
Also let a person wounded.
还让人打伤了
He's still in the hospital.
现在还在医院住着
I can try to turn him around.
我可以试着去策反他
See if we can get through him.
看看能不能通过他
To restrain Chen Duxiu.
来钳制住陈独秀
Put aside what you're doing.
你把手头上的事放一放
Concentrate on this matter
专心办这件事
I'll allocate special funds for you.
我给你拨专款
I'll give you a credit when it's done.
事成之后 我给你报功
Director Xie
谢总监
remember
记住
Don't be exposed at work.
工作的时候千万不要暴露
Your identity in the police department
你在警察厅的身份
Rest assured.
您放心
I am the editor-in-chief of the column of "Gazette"
我是《公言报》的专栏主编
Go ahead
去吧去吧
Fengzai
丰载
Isn't your uncle a congressman?
你叔叔不是国会议员吗
He and Gu Hongming Liu Shipei Huang
他和辜鸿铭 刘师培 黄侃
Good relationship
关系很好
right
对
We call Director Li of the Ministry of Education.
我们叫教育部的李司长
Ask your uncle to meet these professors.
约你叔叔和这几位教授见面
What do you think?
你意下如何
Good!
好啊
This is a wonderful plan.
此计甚妙
I'll inform my uncle.
我去通知我叔叔
Go ahead
快去吧
In this noisy time.
这个乱哄哄的时候
Director Li invited the three of us to dinner.
李司长请我们三个人吃饭
What does he want?
蹊跷 他想干什么
I really don't know.
我也实是不知啊
Director Li of the Ministry of Education.
说是教育部李司长
Long-awaited three people's fame.
久慕我等三人大名
Want to make friends with me.
想和我等交个朋友
so
故
Zhang Changli hosted a banquet for me today.
张长礼今日做东宴请我等
Said to introduce you to each other.
说是介绍大家认识一下
Zhang Changli
张长礼
Why didn't you say so earlier?
你怎么不早说呀
This is the hongmen banquet.
他这是鸿门宴
return
回去
Tang gong
汤公
Let's settle down when we come.
咱们既来之则安之
I'm sure he can't come up with a big name.
谅他也搞不出什么大名堂来
Why don't we wait and see?
咱们何不静观其变呢
You can come.
你们可来了
Tang gong
汤公
Uncle Ji Shenshu
季刚 申叔
Let me introduce you.
来我介绍一下
This is the one who will be promoted to the second minister of education.
这位是即将升任教育部次长的
Director Li
李司长
Tang Gong 'a
汤公啊
Please, please
请请请
Kandaoer
看道儿
come
来
Please.
请 请
Please sit down, please sit down.
请坐 请坐
Please sit down.
诸位 请坐
Three masters, let's sit on the second floor.
三位大师 咱们二楼入席吧
All right, please
也好 请
Dare to ask you two?
敢问二位
Why am I waiting for a banquet today?
今日何故宴请我等哪
I'm not affected by reactive power.
无功不受禄啊
I Gu Hongming never eat nameless seats.
我辜鸿铭从来不吃无名之席
I'd better ask you two to make it clear.
还是请二位把话说清楚的好啊
three's place
三位
Three, let's go upstairs and join the discussion.
三位 还是上楼入座谈吧
Please please please please
请请请 请
please
请
Two places
二位 恕我无礼
I am naturally timid.
本人天生胆小
Today, I am deeply in love.
今日内心十分志恋
Dare not drink this nameless wine.
不敢喝这无名之酒
Please tell us why.
还请二位说清缘由为好
I am old today.
今天我老辜
Come and sit and sit.
来也来了 坐也坐了
Face is enough for you.
面子也给足你们了
If you don't make it clear
如果你们要是不把话说清楚喽
Then I'll grease my feet and slip away.
那我可就脚底抹油溜了
Actually, it's nothing.
其实也不为何事
Li Zhangchang takes office soon.
李司长上任在即
I just want to make friends with three people.
就是想和三位交个朋友
Three don't have to sweat it.
三位不必多心
Let's talk over dinner on the second floor.
咱们还是二楼边吃边谈吧
please
请
This
这 这
Look at this
你看这
this
这
Director Li
李司长
All three are temperamental people.
这三位都是性情中人
Then let's be honest.
那 我们就开诚布公吧
All right, all right.
好 那也好
Three masters!
三位大师啊
Brother in the Ministry of Education
兄弟在教育部
Take the responsibility of managing the university.
担任着管理大学的职责
Since the May 4th Movement
五四运动以来
北京大学在陈独秀李大钊
北京大学在陈独秀 李大钊
And Hu Shi and others.
和胡适等人的煽动下
It's been nearly a month since the strike.
闹罢课已经近一个月了
Education in Beijing has been completely paralyzed.
北京的教育已经完全瘫痪
What a heavy loss!
损失惨重啊
It's painful to think of these things.
想起这些 真让人痛心疾首
For my country.
本人为了国家
And for my own duty.
也为了自己的职责
I would like to ask all the masters to be able to
我愿请各位大师能够在危难之际
Be able to help justice.
能够出面匡扶正义
Go to the lecture hall early to resume teaching.
及早走上讲堂 恢复教学
I'm begging you.
我拜托了
Tang gong
汤公
If the three of you can go to the lecture hall
如果三位能够走上讲堂
Resume teaching
恢复教学
This is Peking University's great education.
此乃北大幸甚 教育幸甚
The country is fortunate.
国家幸甚
Director Li knows three people.
李司长知道三位
Been suppressed by Chen Duxiu for many years
多年被陈独秀压制
Have been depressed and frustrated.
一直抑郁不得志
yes
是啊
He is very willing to do his best for the three leaders.
他非常愿意为三位出头尽力
Stand up for us
替我们出头
yes
是啊
Good!
好啊
What's the first step?
那怎么个出头法呢
I'd like to hear all about it.
我愿闻其详
That's it.
是这样
If the three masters can help the government
如果三位大师能够帮助政府
Restore teaching order as soon as possible
及早恢复教学秩序
You are the heroes of Peking University.
那你们就是北大的功臣了
Brothers are willing to protect three masters.
兄弟愿保三位大师
And Hu Renyuan, the new president of Peking University.
和北京大学新任校长胡仁源
Take charge of Peking University together
一同执掌北大
how about
怎么样
I said, why am I so confused today?
我说我今天怎么这么六神无主呢
It turned out to be a ghost.
原来是撞见鬼了
Although I don't agree with Cai Yuanpei
我虽然不赞同蔡元培
Chen Duxiu Hu Shi's Cultural View
陈独秀 胡适的文化观
But I haven't forgotten that I am a Chinese.
但我没有忘记我是一个中国人
I absolutely don't like queen.
我绝对不赞后
The government signed this traitorous Paris agreement.
政府签这个卖国的巴黎协定
I don't agree with the students' strike
我是不赞同学生们罢课
but
但是
And I will never betray my students.
我也绝对不会出卖我的学生
You look down on me.
你们太小看我了
A table banquet can buy me off.
一桌酒席就能收买我啊
You gangsters!
你们这些宵小之徒
The heart can be punished.
其心可诛
Three, don't go. Three
三位别走 三位
Don't be so shameless
做人不可如此无耻
This
这 这
this
这
Blame Wu Bingxiang for being such an asshole.
都怪吴炳湘这个浑蛋
He screwed things up.
他把事情搞砸了
This this this
这 这 这
Wrong door, right?
走错门了吧
young man
老弟
this
这个
I heard that bro was gloriously wounded.
听说老弟光荣负伤
I was entrusted by the Propaganda Department of Beijing Federation of Students.
我受北京学联宣传部的委托
It's not respectful to visit specially.
特来探望 不成敬意
this is a mere token of my indebtedness
不成敬意
Xuelian publicity department
学联宣传部
Aren't you already expelled from Peking University?
你不是早都被北大开除了吗
How to become the propaganda department again?
怎么又成宣传部的人了
Dude!
老弟呀
I was expelled from Peking University.
我被北大开除不假
But I am now.
可我现在是
"Gazette"
《公言报》
Editor-in-Chief of Xuehai Chunqiu
《学海春秋》 栏的主编
Our program supports the student movement.
我们这个栏目是支持学生运动的
Under the leadership of the Propaganda Department of Beijing Federation of Students.
是受北京学联宣传部的领导
Responsible for reporting student sports.
专门负责报道学生运动情况的
Isn't "Gazette" a newspaper of Anfu Department?
《公言报》 不是安福系的报吗
Now you also support patriotism.
现在也支持爱国了
What happened to Anfu?
安福系怎么了
There are patriots in the Fu family.
安福系里也有爱国的
Take me for example.
你就拿我来说吧
Although I don't approve.
我虽然不赞成
What's your new culture?
你们搞什么新文化
I don't approve of your work-study mutual assistance.
我不赞成你们搞什么工读互助
But I am firmly opposed to the Paris Peace Treaty.
可我是坚决反对巴黎和约的
My hometown is also from Shandong.
我老家也是山东的
I will never allow Shandong
我绝不允许把山东
Give it to the Japanese
拱手让给日本人
There are also traitors in Shandong.
山东也有卖国贼
If you are really patriotic
你要是真爱国呀
Just go to the thousand points and do something practical.
你就去千点实事
Don't talk to me about this here.
别在这儿跟我说这些有的没的
I said bro.
我说老弟啊
You can't look at people under the door.
你可不能门缝里看人啊
My editor-in-chief column Xuehai Chunqiu
我主编的 《学海春秋》 栏目
But it was appointed by Beijing Federation of Students.
可是北京学联指定的
A column to publicize the student movement
宣传学生运动的栏目
Come and see.
来 你看
This is my interview card.
这是我的采访证
Look at this
你看这
picture
照片
jab
戳
The real thing is not to be cheated.
货真价实的 不蒙人
auv nana
那这么说
Don't look at yourself in March.
土别三月当刮自相看了
Be happy first.
你先高兴着
I go out for activities.
我出去活动活动
You don't go
你别走
You are a wounded hero.
你是受伤的英雄
He is also the eldest son of Chen Duxiu, leader of the student movement.
又是学运领袖陈独秀的大公子
I was ordered to interview you.
我是奉命来采访你
I want to write a report for you.
想给你写一篇报道
Interview again
又采访
Last time, I used the interview trick to set Liu Mei's words.
上一回就用采访这招套柳眉的话
You want to set me up this time.
这回还想来套我的
Don't mention Liu Mei to me.
你别给我提柳眉
I get angry when you mention Liu Mei.
你一提柳眉我就来气
Besides, who set who in the last interview?
再说了 上次采访谁套谁的话啊
You know better than I do.
你心里比我清楚
Didn't you ask for it?
那不是你自找的吗
I'll tell you clearly.
我明确地告诉你
I don't give interviews.
我不接受采访
Don't waste time here.
别在这儿浪费时间
Fine, then we won't interview today.
行那咱们今天不采访
Can I tell you something?
我跟你说个事 行吧
About your father Chen Duxiu
关于你父亲陈独秀的事情
Not interested in listening.
没兴趣听
Don't go yet. Sit down.
你先别走 你先坐
you listen to me
你坐下 你听我说
This is always important. Sit down.
这个事非常重要 你坐
That's it.
是这样
Recently, our column "Learning the Sea Spring and Autumn"
最近我们《学海春秋》栏目
Received many letters from readers and some leaflets.
收到了很多读者来信和一些传单
It's all about your father
都是对你父亲
excuse me/ sorry /feel bad/can't bring myself to ...
不好意思
It's all about your father Chen Duxiu
都是对你父亲陈独秀
A very unfavorable thing
非常不利的事情
We don't know what to do with it.
我们不知道该怎么处理
I want to hear your opinion.
想听听你的意见
What do you mean, don't look?
什么意思啊 不看啊
Chen Duxiu, since coming to the University
陈独秀自从来到北大
There are people who think about other things every day.
想坏他事的人天天都有
Newspapers even framed rumors.
报纸更是诬陷造谣
You take these old sesame seeds and rotten millet things
你拿这些陈芝麻烂谷子的事
What's the point of telling me?
跟我说有什么意义呀
You see clearly.
你看清楚
This isn't the news of stale sesame seeds and rotten millet.
这可不是陈芝麻烂谷子的消息
This is the present fact.
这是眼前的事实
This pile
这一大堆
It's all the statements of the risk taker.
全都是冒击者的陈述材料
it's up to you
你自己看
You asked my opinion about Chen Duxiu.
陈独秀的事 你问我的意见
What's your heart about Ann?
你安的什么心啊
Ah, brother
老弟啊
That's very kind of me.
我可真是好心
Think about it. I have these materials.
你想想看 这些材料在我手里
Once it's in the newspaper
一旦登了报纸
That's explosive news.
那就是爆炸性的新闻
Then you won't miss it.
那你不会不登啊
It's not up to me whether it's boarded or not.
它登不登不是我说了算呀
Chen Duxiu and Cai Yuanpei
陈独秀和蔡元培
Although I don't deal with them
我虽然跟他们不对付
But I know the weight.
但是我知道轻重
It is the critical moment of the student movement.
眼前正是学生运动的关键时刻
Cai Yuanpei ran away
蔡元培跑了
Chen Duxiu is recognized as a young teacher.
陈独秀是公认的青年导师
Some people even say
有人甚至说
He said he was the commander behind the May 4th Movement.
说他是五四运动的幕后总指挥
At this critical moment
在这个关键时刻
This key figure has caused such a big scandal.
这个关键人物闹出这么大的丑闻
This pair of student movements
这对学生运动
Will be a devastating blow.
将是一次毁灭性的打击
Do you know
你知道吗
I, as a
我作为一个
Editor-in-chief of a newspaper column under the leadership of a student union.
一个学联领导下报纸栏目的主编
I can't watch students' sports collapse.
我不能眼看着学生运动天折
Do you understand?
你懂吗
What should I do then?
那我该怎么做呀
You are his son.
你是他儿子呀
It is your duty to stop your father.
你有责任阻止你的父亲
Don't do these things again at this time.
不要在这个时候再干这些蠢事
Stop smearing the student movement.
不要再给学生运动抹黑了
Newspapers smear every day.
报纸天天抹黑
But that's not evidence.
但那不是证据
Who is the witness?
谁是人证
Let him confront me.
让他来跟我对质
If what he said is true
他要是说的是真的
I, Chen Yannian
我陈延年
Break up with Chen Duxiu now
现在就跟陈独秀断绝关系
We are north
我们北
Many of their professors at Peking University are witnesses.
他们北大很多教授都是人证
Who are many professors?
很多教授是谁啊
If it is against the new culture of the hundred schools.
若是反对新文化的复百派
I don't think I can fully believe it.
想必也不能完全相信吧
Trekking
行行
Then I'll tell you two
那我就跟你说两个
It's not retro
不是复古派的
Shen Yinmo, the peer editor of New Youth
《新青年》 的同人编辑沈尹默
And an old friend of your father's.
和你父亲的老朋友
Principal Tang Erhe
专校长汤尔和
These two are from the same year.
这两个可都是当年
Recommend your father's great benefactor
力荐你父亲的大恩人
Not long ago, it was them.
前不久 就是他俩
Force mainly from your father.
力主要免去你父亲
Senior position in liberal arts
文科学长的职务
Yannian
延年
I know how you feel right now.
我知道你现在心里什么滋味
Knowing that my father is such a person
得知自己父亲是这样的一个人
I can understand how you feel now.
我能理解你现在的感受
such
这样
I'll put these things here
我把这些东西放这儿
Take a look when you are free.
你有空就看看
Yannian
延年
Facts are facts.
事实就是事实
Dare to face it?
敢不敢面对
Look at yourself.
看你自己了